<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules_basic.sch"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="ppp.01877">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">As a Strong Bird on Pinions Free and Other Poems</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Walt Whitman</author>
            <editor role="general">Ed Folsom</editor>
            <editor role="general">Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="sd">Sara Duke</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2016</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>ppp.01877</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>The text of the original item is in the public domain.</p><p>The text encoding was created and/or prepared by the <title level="m">Walt Whitman Archive</title> and is licensed under a <ref target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License</ref> (CC BY 4.0). Any reuse of this material should credit the <title level="m">Walt Whitman Archive</title>.</p><p>Permission to reproduce the graphic images of the original item has been granted by the owners of the original for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</author>
                  <title>As a Strong Bird on Pinions Free and Other Poems</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Washington, D.C.</pubPlace>
                     <publisher><!-- FILL IN TEXT HERE --></publisher>
                     <!-- Book is printed by S.W. Green, Printer, 16 and 18 Jacob Street, New-York. -->
                     <date xml:id="dat1" when="1872">1872</date>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository><!-- FILL IN TEXT HERE --></repository>
                  <idno><!-- FILL IN TEXT HERE --></idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p><!-- AN EDITOR WILL FILL IN THIS INFORMATION. --></p>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2016-04-11" who="#sd">Transcription and Encoding</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   
   <text type="printed">
      <front> 
         <titlePage>
            
            <docTitle>
               <titlePart type="main"><hi rend="italic">As a Strong Bird on Pinions Free.</hi></titlePart>
               <titlePart><hi rend="italic">AND OTHER POEMS.</hi></titlePart>
            </docTitle>
            
            <docImprint>
               <pubPlace>WASHINGTON, D.C.</pubPlace>
               
               <date>1872</date>
            </docImprint>
            
            <pb facs="ppp.01875.007.jpg" xml:id="leaf003v1" n="N/A" type="verso"/>
            
            <!--Verso of title page.-->
                   
            <docImprint>
               Entered, according to Act of Congress, in the year 1872, by
               WALT WHITMAN, 
               In the Office of the Librarian of Congress, at Washington.
            </docImprint>
            
            <docImprint>S.W. G<hi rend="smallcaps">reen</hi>, Printer, 16 and 18 Jacob Street, New&#8211;York,</docImprint>
            
         </titlePage>
         <div1 type="contents">
            <p>
            <table>
               <head type="main-authorial">CONTENTS.</head>
               <row>
                  <cell></cell>
                  <cell>PAGE</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>P<hi rend="smallcaps">reface</hi>................................................</cell>
                  <cell>v</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>O<hi rend="smallcaps">ne</hi> S<hi rend="smallcaps">ong</hi>, A<hi rend="smallcaps">merica, before</hi> I <hi rend="smallcaps">Go</hi>.......................</cell>
                  <cell>xi</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>S<hi rend="smallcaps">ouvenirs of</hi> D<hi rend="smallcaps">emocracy</hi>...............................</cell>
                  <cell>xiii</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>A<hi rend="smallcaps">s a</hi> S<hi rend="smallcaps">trong</hi> B<hi rend="smallcaps">ird on</hi> P<hi rend="smallcaps">inions Free</hi>.....................</cell>
                  <cell>1</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>T<hi rend="smallcaps">he</hi> M<hi rend="smallcaps">ystic</hi> T<hi rend="smallcaps">rumpeter</hi>................................</cell>
                  <cell>8</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>O S<hi rend="smallcaps">tar of</hi> F<hi rend="smallcaps">rance</hi>!..................................</cell>
                  <cell>13</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>V<hi rend="smallcaps">irginia</hi>&#8212;T<hi rend="smallcaps">he</hi> W<hi rend="smallcaps">est</hi>...................................</cell>
                  <cell>15</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>B<hi rend="smallcaps">y</hi> B<hi rend="smallcaps">road</hi> P<hi rend="smallcaps">otomac's</hi> S<hi rend="smallcaps">hore</hi>............................</cell>
                  <cell>16</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>A<hi rend="smallcaps">dvertisement.</hi></cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            </p>
            
            </div1>
         <div1 type="preface">
            <head type="main-authorial">PREFACE.</head>
            <p>T<hi rend="smallcaps">he</hi> impetus and ideas urging me, for some years past, to 
            an utterance, or attempt at utterance, of New World songs, 
            and an epic of Democracy, having already had their published 
            expression, as well as I can expect to give it, in L<hi rend="smallcaps">eaves of</hi> 
            G<hi rend="smallcaps">rass</hi>, the present and any future pieces from me are really but 
            the surplusage forming after that Volume, or the wake eddying 
            behind it. I fulfilled in that an imperious conviction, and the 
            commands of my nature as total and irresistible as those which 
            make the sea flow, or the globe revolve. But of this Supplementary 
            Volume, I confess I am not so certain. Having from 
            early manhood abandoned the business pursuits and applications 
            usual in my time and country, and obediently yielded 
            myself up ever since to the impetus mentioned, and to the work of 
            expressing those ideas, it may be that mere habit has got dominion 
            of me, when there is no real need of saying any thing further....
            But what is life but an experiment? and mortality but an exercise? 
            with reference to results beyond. And so shall my poems 
            be. If incomplete here, and superfluous there, <hi rend="italic">n'importe</hi>&#8212;the 
            earnest trial and persistent exploration shall at least be mine, 
            and other success failing, shall be success enough. I have been 
            more anxious, anyhow, to suggest the songs of vital endeavor, 
            and manly evolution, and furnish something for races of outdoor 
            athletes, than to make perfect rhymes, or reign in the parlors. 
            I ventured from the beginning, my own way, taking chances&#8212;and 
            would keep on venturing.</p>
            <p>I will therefore not conceal from any persons, known or unknown 
            to me, who take interest in the matter, that I have the 
            ambition of devoting yet a few years to poetic composition.... 
            The might present age! To absorb, and express in poetry, 
            any thing of it&#8212;of its world&#8212;America&#8212;cities and States&#8212;the 
            years, the events of our Nineteenth Century&#8212;the rapidity of 
            movement&#8212;the violent contrasts, fluctuations of light and shade, 
            of hope and fear&#8212;the entire revolution made by science in the 
            poetic method&#8212;these great new underlying facts and new ideas 
            rushing and spreading everywhere;&#8212;Truly a mighty age! As 
            if in some colossal drama, acted again like those of old, under 
            the open sun, the Nations of our time, and all the characteristics 
            of Civilization, seem hurrying, stalking across, flitting from wing 
            to wing, gathering, closing up, toward some long&#8211;prepared, most 
            tremendous denouement. Not to conclude the infinite scenas 
            of the race's life and toil and happiness and sorrow, but haply 
            that the boards be cleared from oldest, worst incumbrances, accumulations, 
            and Man resume the eternal play anew, and under 
            happier, freer auspices.... To me, the United States are important 
            because, in this colossal drama, they are unquestionably 
            designated for the leading parts, for many a century to come. 
            In them History and Humanity seem to seek to culminate. Our 
            broad areas are even now the busy theatre of plots, passions, 
            interests, and suspended problems, compared to which the intrigues 
            of the past of Europe, the wars of dynasties, the score 
            of kings and kingdoms, and even the development of peoples, 
            as hitherto, exhibit scales of measurement comparatively narrow 
            and trivial. And on these areas of ours, as on a stage, sooner 
            or later, something like an <hi rend="italic">eclaircissement</hi> of all the past civilization 
            of Europe and Asia is probably to be evolved.</p>
            <p>The leading parts.... Not to be acted, emulated here, by us 
            again, that role till now foremost in History&#8212;Not to become a 
            conqueror nation, or to achieve the glory of mere military, or 
            diplomatic, or commercial superiority&#8212;but to become the grand 
            Producing Land of nobler Men and Women&#8212;of copious races, 
            cheerful, healthy, tolerant, free&#8212;To become the most friendly 
            Nation, (the United States indeed,)&#8212;the modern composite 
            Nation, formed from all, with room for all, welcoming all immigrant&#8212;accepting 
            the work of our own interior development, as 
            the work fitly filling ages and ages to come;&#8212;the leading Nation 
            of peace, but neither ignorant or incapable of being the 
            leading Nation of war;&#8212;not the Man's Nation only, but the 
            Woman's Nation&#8212;a land of splendid mothers, daughters, sisters, 
            wives.</p>
            <p>Our America to&#8211;day I consider in many respects as but indeed 
            a vast seething mass of <hi rend="italic">materials</hi>, ampler, better, (worse also,) 
            than previously known&#8212;eligible to be used to carry toward its 
            crowning stage, and build for good the great ideal Nationality of 
            the future, the nation of the Body and the Soul,<ref target="#fn1">*</ref>&#8212;no limit 
            here to land, help, opportunities, mines, products, demands, 
            supplies, &#38;c;&#8212;with (I think) our political organization, 
            National, State, and Municipal, permanently established, as far 
            ahead as we can calculate&#8212;but, so far, no social, literary, religious, 
            or esthetic organizations, consistent with our politics, or 
            becoming to us&#8212;which organizations can only come, in time, 
            through native schools or teachers of great Democratic Ideas, 
            Religion&#8212;through Science, which now, like a new sunrise, ascending, 
            begins to illuminate all&#8212;and through our own begotten 
            Poets and Literatuses.... (The moral of a late well&#8211;written 
            book on Civilization seems to be that the only real foundation 
            walls and basis&#8212;and also <hi rend="italic">sine qua non</hi> afterward&#8212;of true and 
            full Civilization, is the eligibility and certainty of boundless products 
            for feeding, clothing, sheltering every body&#8212;perennial 
            fountains of physical and domestic comfort, with intercommunication, 
            and with civil and ecclesiastical freedom;&#8212;and that 
            then the esthetic and mental business will take care of itself.... 
            Well, the United States have established this basis, and 
            upon scales of extent, variety, vitality, and continuity, rivaling 
            those of Nature; and have now to proceed to build an Edifice 
            upon it. I say this Edifice is only to be fitly built by new
            
               <note xml:id="fn1" type="footnote" place="bottom">
                  * The problems of the achievement of this crowning stage through future 
                  first&#8211;class National Singers, Orators, Artists, and others&#8212;of creating in literature 
                  an <hi rend="italic">imaginative</hi> New World, the correspondent and counterpart of the 
                  current Scientific and Political New Worlds&#8212;and the perhaps distant, but still 
                  delightful prospect, (for our children, if not in our own day,) of delivering 
                  America, and, indeed, all Christian lands everywhere, from the thin, moribund, 
                  and watery, but appallingly extensive nuisance of conventional poetry&#8212;by putting 
                  something really alive and substantial in its place&#8212;I have undertaken 
                  to grapple with, and argue in D<hi rend="smallcaps">emocratic</hi> V<hi rend="smallcaps">istas</hi>.
               </note>
               
            Literatures, especially the Poetic. I say a modern Image&#8211;Making 
            creation is indispensable to fuse and express the modern Political 
            and Scientific creations&#8212;and then the Trinity will be complete.)</p>
            
            <p>When I commenced, years ago, elaborating the plan of my 
            poems, and continued turning over that plan, and shifting it in 
            my mind through many years, (from the age of twenty&#8211;eight to 
            thirty&#8211;five,) experimenting much, and writing and abandoning
             much, one deep purpose underlay the others, and has underlain 
            it and its execution ever since&#8212;and that has been the Religious 
            purpose. Amid many changes, and a formulation taking far 
            different shape from what I at first supposed, this basic purpose 
            has never been departed from in the composition of my verses. 
            Not of course to exhibit itself in the old ways, as in writing 
            hymns or psalms with an eye to the church&#8211;pew, or to express 
            conventional poetism, or the sickly yearnings of devotees, but in 
            new ways, and aiming at the widest sub&#8211;bases and inclusions of 
            Humanity, and tallying the fresh air of sea and land. I will see, 
            (said I to myself,) whether there is not, for my purposes as poet, 
            a Religion, and a sound Religious germenancy in the average 
            Human Race, at least in their modern development in the United 
            States, and in the hardy common fibre and native yearnings and 
            elements, deeper and larger, and affording more profitable returns, 
            than all mere sects or churches&#8212; as boundless, joyous, and vital 
            as Nature itself&#8212;A germenancy that has too long been unencouraged, 
            unsung, almost unknown.... With Science, the Old 
            Theology of the East, long in its dotage, begins evidently to die 
            and disappear. But (to my mind) Science&#8212;and may be such 
            will prove its principal service&#8212;as evidently prepares the way 
            for One indescribably grander&#8212;Time's young but perfect offspring&#8212;
            the New Theology&#8212;heir of he West&#8212;lusty and loving, 
            and wondrous beautiful. For America, and for to&#8211;day, just the 
            same as any day, the supreme and final Science is the Science of 
            God&#8212;what we call science being only its minister&#8212;as Democracy 
            is or shall be also. And a poet of America (I said) must fill himself 
            with such thoughts, and chant his best out of them......
            And as those were the convictions and aims, for good or bad, of 
            L<hi rend="smallcaps">eaves of</hi> G<hi rend="smallcaps">rass</hi>, they are no less the intention of this Volume. 
            As there can be, in my opinion, no sane and complete Personality&#8212;
            nor any grand and electric Nationality, without the stock element 
            of Religion imbuing all the other elements, (like heat in 
            chemistry, invisible itself, but the life of all visible life,) so there 
            can be no Poetry worthy the name without that element behind 
            all...... The time has certainly come to begin to discharge the 
            idea of Religion, in the United States, from mere ecclesiasticism, 
            and from Sundays and churches and church&#8211;going, and assign it 
            to that general position, chiefest, most indispensable, most exhilarating, 
            to which the others are to be adjusted, inside of all 
            human character, and education, and affairs. The people, especially 
            the young men and women of America, must begin to learn 
            that Religion, (like Poetry,) is something far, far different from 
            what they supposed. It is, indeed, too important to the power 
            and perpetuity of the New World to be consigned any longer to 
            the churches, old or new, Catholic or Protestant&#8212;Saint this, or 
            Saint that.... It must be consigned henceforth to Democracy 
            <hi rend="italic">en masse</hi>, and to Literature. It must enter into the Poems of 
            the Nation. It must make the Nation.</p>
            
            <p>The Four Years' War is over&#8212;and in the peaceful, strong, 
            exciting, fresh occasions of To&#8211;day, and of the Future that 
            strange, sad war is hurrying even now to be forgotten. The 
            camp, the drill, the lines of sentries, the prison,s the hospitals,
            &#8212;(ah! the hospitals!)&#8212;all have passed away&#8212;all seem now 
            like a dream. A new race, a young and lusty generation, 
            already sweeps in with oceanic currents, obliterating that war, 
            and all its scars, its mounded graves, and all its reminiscences 
            of hatred, conflict, death. So let it be obliterated. I say the 
            life of the present and the future makes undeniable demands 
            upon us each and all, South, North, East, West.... To help 
            put the United States (even if only in imagination) hand in 
            hand, in one unbroken circle in a chant&#8212;To rouse them to the 
            unprecedented grandeur of the part they are to play, and are 
            even now playing&#8212;to the thought of their great Future, and 
            the attitude conformed to it&#8212;especially their great Esthetic, 
            Moral, Scientific Future, (of which their vulgar material and 
            political present is but as the preparatory tuning of instruments 
            by an orchestra,)&#8212;these, as hitherto, are still, for me, among 
            my hopes, ambitions.</p>
            
            <p>L<hi rend="smallcaps">eaves of</hi> G<hi rend="smallcaps">rass</hi>, already published, is, in its intentions, the 
            song of a great composite <hi rend="italic">Democratic Individual</hi>, male or 
            female. And following on and amplifying the same purpose, I 
            suppose I have in my mind to run through the chants of this 
            Volume, (if ever completed,) the thread&#8211;voice, more or less audible, 
            of an aggregated, inseparable, unprecedented, vast, composite, 
            electric <hi rend="italic">Democratic Nationality</hi>.</p>
            
            <p>Purposing, then, to still fill out, from time to time through 
            years to come, the following Volume, (unless prevented,) I conclude 
            this Preface to the first installment of it, pencilled in 
            the open air, on my fifty&#8211;third birth&#8211;day, by wafting to you, 
            dear Reader, whoever you are, (from amid the fresh scent of 
            the grass, the pleasant coolness of he forenoon breeze, the lights 
            and shades of tree&#8211;boughs silently dappling and playing around 
            me, and the notes of the cat&#8211;bird for undertone and accompaniment,) 
            my true good&#8211;will and love.</p>
            <p>Washington, D.C., May 31, 1872.        W.W.</p>
         </div1>
      </front>
         <body>
            <div1>
            <lg type="poem">
               <head type="main-authorial"><hi rend="italic">ONE SONG, AMERICA, BEFORE I GO.</hi></head>
               <lg type="linegroup">
                  <l>O<hi rend="smallcaps">ne</hi> song, America, before I go,</l>
                  <l>I'd sing, o'er all the rest, with trumpet sound,</l>
                  <l>For thee&#8212;the Future.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg type="linegroup">
                  <l>I'd so a seed for thee of endless Nationality;</l>
                  <l>I'd fashion thy Ensemble, including Body and <lb/>Soul;</l>
                  <l>I'd show, away ahead, thy real Union, and how it <lb/>may be <choice><sic>accomplish'd</sic><corr>accomplished</corr></choice>.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg type="linegroup">
                  <l>(The paths to the House I seek to make,</l>
                  <l>But leave to those to come, the House itself.)</l>
               </lg>
               <lg type="linegroup">
                  <l>Belief I sing&#8212;and Preparation;</l>
                  <l>As Life and Nature are not great with reference to <lb/>the Present only,</l>
                  <l>But greater still from what is yet to come</l>
                  <l>Out of that formula for Thee I sing.</l>
               </lg>
            </lg>
            </div1>
            <div1>
            <lg type="poem">
               <head type="main-authorial"><hi rend="italic">SOUVENIRS OF DEMOCRACY.</hi></head>
               <lg type="linegroup">
                  <l>T<hi rend="smallcaps">he</hi> business man, the acquirer vast,</l>
                  <l>After assiduous years, surveying results, preparing <lb/>for departure,</l>
                  <l>Devises houses and lands to his children&#8212;bequeaths <lb/>stocks, goods&#8212;funds for a school or <choice><sic>his&#8211;<lb/>pital</sic><corr>hospital</corr></choice>,</l>
                  <l>Leaves money to certain companions to buy tokens, <lb/>souvenirs of gems and gold;</l>
                  <l>Parceling out with care&#8212;And then, to prevent all <lb/>cavil,</l>
                  <l>His name to his testament formally signs.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg type="linegroup">
                  <l>But I, my life surveying,</l>
                  <l>With nothing to show, to devise, from its idle <lb/>years,</l>
                  <l>Nor houses, nor lands&#8212;nor tokens of gems or gold <lb/>for my friends,</l>
                  <l>Only these Souvenirs of Democracy&#8212;In them&#8212;in <lb/>all my songs&#8212;behind me leaving,</l>
                  <l>To You, whoever you are, (bathing, leavening this <lb/>leaf especially with my breath&#8212;pressing on it <lb/>a moment with my own hands;</l>
                  <l>&#8212;Here! feel how the pulse beats in m wrists!&#8212; <lb/>how my heart's&#8211;blood is swelling, <choice><sic>contract&#8211;<lb/>ing</sic><corr>contracting</corr></choice>!)</l>
                  <l>I will You, in all, Myself, with promise to never <lb/>desert you,</l>
                  <l>To which I sign my name,</l>
                  <l>Walt Whitman</l>
               </lg>
            </lg>
            </div1>
            
            <div1>   
            <lg type="poem">
               <head type="main-authorial"><hi rend="italic">AS A STRONG BIRD ON PINIONS FREE.</hi></head>
                 <lg type="section"><head type="sub">1.</head>
                   <lg type="linegroup">
                     <l>As a strong bird on pinions free,</l>
                     <l>Joyous, the amplest spaces heavenward cleaving,</l>
                     <l>Such be the thought I'd think to&#8211;day of thee, America,</l>
                     <l>Such be the recitative I'd bring to&#8211;day for thee.<ref target="#fn2">*</ref></l>
                   </lg>
                   <lg type="linegroup">
                     <l>The conceits of the poets of other lands I bring thee <lb/>not,</l>
                     <l>Nor the compliments that have served their turn so <lb/>long,</l>
                     <l>Nor rhyme&#8212;nor the classics&#8212;nor perfume of foreign <lb/>court, or indoor library;</l>
                     <l>But an odor I'd bring to&#8211;day as from forests of <lb/>pine in the north, in Maine&#8212;or breath of an <choice><sic>Illi&#8211; <lb/>nois</sic><corr>Illinois</corr></choice> prairie,</l>
                     <l>With open airs of Virginia, or Georgia, or Tennessee <lb/>&#8212;or from Texas uplands, or Florida's glades,</l>
                     <l>With presentment of Yellowstone's scenes, or <choice><sic>Yo&#8211; <lb/>semite</sic><corr>Yosemite</corr></choice>;</l>
                     <l>And murmuring under, pervading all, I'd bring the <lb/>rustling sea&#8211;sound,</l>
                     <l>That endlessly sounds from the two great seas of the <lb/>world.</l>
                                    
               <note xml:id="fn2" type="footnote" place="bottom">
                  * Commencement Poem, Dartmouth College, N.H., June 26, 
                  1872, on invitation United Literary Societies.
               </note>
                      
                      <l>And for thy subtler sense, subtler refrains, O Union!</l>
                      <l>Preludes of intellect tallying these and thee&#8212;<choice><sic>mind&#8211; <lb/>formulas</sic><corr>mind&#8211;formulas</corr></choice> fitted for thee&#8212;real, and sane, and large
                         <lb/>as these and thee;</l>
                      <l>Thou, mounting higher, diving deeper than we knew <lb/>&#8212;thou transcendental Union!</l>
                      <l>By thee Fact to be justified&#8212;blended with God:</l>
                      <l>Through thy Idea&#8212;lo! the immortal Reality!</l>
                      <l>Through thy Reality&#8212;lo! the immortal Idea!</l>
                   </lg>
                 </lg>
               
                 <lg type="section"><head type="sub">2.</head>
                    <lg type="linegroup">
                       <l>Brain of the new World! what a task is thine!</l>
                       <l>To formulate the Modern..:.. Out of the peerless <lb/>grandeur of the modern,</l>
                       <l>Out of Thyself&#8212;comprising Science&#8212;to recast <lb/>Poems, Churches, Art,</l>
                       <l>(Recast&#8212;may&#8211;be discard them, end them&#8212;May&#8211;be <lb/>their work is done&#8212;who knows?)</l>
                       <l>By vision, hand, conception, on the background of <lb/>the mighty past, the dead,</l>
                       <l>To limn, with absolute faith, the mighty living <choice><sic>pre&#8211; <lb/>sent</sic><corr>present</corr></choice>.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg type="linegroup">
                       <l>And yet, thou living, present brain! heir of the dead, <lb/> the Old World brain!</l>
                       <l>Though that lay folded, like an unborn babe, within its <lb/>folds so long!</l>
                       <l>Thou carefully prepared by it so long!&#8212;haply thou <lb/> but unfoldest it&#8212;only maturest it;</l>
                       <l>It to eventuate in thee&#8212;the esence of the by&#8211;gone <lb/>time <choice><sic>contain'd</sic><corr>contained</corr></choice> in thee;</l>
                       <l>Its poems, churches, arts, unwitting to themselves, <lb/>destined with reference to thee,</l>
                       <l>The fruit of all the Old, ripening to&#8211;day in thee.</l>
                    </lg>
                 </lg>
               
               <lg type="section"><head type="sub">3.</head>
                  <lg type="linegroup">
                     <l>Sail&#8212;sail thy best, ship of Democracy!</l>
                     <l>Of value is thy freight&#8212;'tis not the Present only,</l>
                     <l>The Past is also stored in thee!</l>
                     <l>Thou holdest not the venture of thyself alone&#8212;not of <lb/>thy western continent alone;</l>
                     <l>Earth's <hi rend="italic">r&#233;sum&#233;</hi> entire floats on thy keel, O ship&#8212;is <lb/>steadied by thy spars;</l>
                     <l>With thee Time voyages in trust&#8212;the antecedent <lb/>nations sink or swim with thee;</l>
                     <l>With all their ancient struggles, martyrs, heroes, <lb/>epics, wars, thou <choice><sic>bear'st</sic><corr>bearest</corr></choice> the other continents;</l>
                     <l>Theirs, theirs as much as thine, the <choice><sic>destination&#8211; <lb/>port</sic><corr>destination&#8211;port</corr></choice> triumphant:</l>
                     <l>&#8212;Steer, steer with good strong hand and wary eye, O <lb/>helmsman&#8212;thou carryest great companions,</l>
                     <l>Venerable, priestly Asia sails this day with thee,</l>
                     <l>And royal, feudal Europe sails with thee.</l>
                  </lg>
               </lg>
               
               <lg type="section"><head type="sub">4.</head>
                  <lg type="linegroup">
                     <l>Beautiful World of new, superber Birth, that rises to <lb/>my eyes,</l>
                     <l>Like a limitless golden cloud, filling the western sky;</l>
                     <l>Emblem of general maternity, lifted above all;</l>
                     <l>Sacred shape of the bearer of daughters and sons;</l>
                     <l>Out of thy teeming womb, thy giant babes in <choice><sic>cease&#8211; <lb/>less</sic><corr>ceaseless</corr></choice> procession issuing,</l>
                     <l>Acceding from such gestation, taking and giving <choice><sic>con&#8211; <lb/>tinual</sic><corr>continual</corr></choice> strength and life;</l>
                     <l>World of the Real! world of the twain in one!</l>
                     <l>World of the Soul&#8212;born by the world of the real <lb/>alone&#8212;led to identiy, body, by it alone;</l>
                     <l>Yet in beginning only&#8212;incalculable masses of <choice><sic>compo&#8211; <lb/>site</sic><corr>composite</corr></choice>, precious materials,</l>
                     <l>by history's cycles forwarded&#8212;by every nation, <choice><sic>lan&#8211; <lb/>guage</sic><corr>language</corr></choice>, hither sent,</l>
                     <l>Ready, collected here&#8212;a freer, vast, electric World, to <lb/>be constructed here,</l>
                     <l>(The true New World&#8212;the world of orbic Science, <lb/>Morals, Literatures to come,)</l>
                     <l>Thou Wonder World, yet undefined, <choice><sic>unform'd</sic><corr>unformed</corr></choice>&#8212; <lb/>neither do I define thee;</l>
                     <l>How can I pierce the impenetrable blank of the <lb/>future?</l>
                     <l>I feel thy ominous greatness, evil as well as good;</l>
                     <l>I watch thee, advancing, absorbing the present, <lb/>transcending the past;</l>
                     <l>I see thy light lighting and thy shadow shadowing, <lb/>as if the entire globe;</l>
                     <l>But I do not undertake to define thee&#8212;hardly to <choice><sic>com&#8211; <lb/>prehend</sic><corr>comprehend</corr></choice>thee;</l>
                     <l>I but thee name&#8212;thee prophecy&#8212;as now!</l>
                     <l>I merely thee ejaculate!</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg type="linegroup">
                     <l>Thee in thy future;</l>
                     <l>Thee in thy only permanent life, career&#8212;thy own <lb/> <choice><sic>unloosen'd</sic><corr>unloosened</corr></choice> mind&#8212;thy soaring spirit;</l>
                     <l>The as another equally needed sun, America&#8212;<choice><sic>ra&#8211; <lb/>diant</sic><corr>radiant</corr></choice>, ablaze, swift&#8211;moving, fructifying all;</l>
                     <l>Thee! risen in thy potent cheerfulness and joy&#8212;thy <lb/>endless, great hilarity!</l>
                     <l>(Scattering for good the cloud that hung so long&#8212; <lb/>that <choice><sic>weigh'd</sic><corr>weighed</corr></choice> so long upon the mind of man,</l>
                     <l>The doubt, suspicion, dread, of gradual, certain <choice><sic>deca&#8211; <lb/>dence</sic><corr>decadence</corr></choice> of man;)</l>
                     <l>Thee in thy larger, saner breeds of Female, Male&#8212; <lb/>thee in thy athletes, moral, spiritual, South, <lb/>North, West, East,</l>
                     <l>(To thy immortal breasts, Mother of All, thy every daughter, son, <choice><sic>endear'd</sic><corr>endeared</corr></choice> alike, forever equal;)</l>
                     <l>Thee in thy own musicians, singers, artists, unborn <lb/>yet, but certain;</l>
                     <l>Thee in thy moral wealth and civilization, (until <lb/>which thy proudest material wealth and <choice><sic>civiliza&#8211; <lb/>tion</sic><corr>civilization</corr></choice> must remain in 
                     vain;)</l>
                     <l>Thee in thy all&#8211;supplying, all&#8211;enclosing Worship&#8212; <lb/>thee in no single bible, savior merely,</l>
                     <l>Thy saviours countless, latent within thyself&#8212;thy <lb/>bibles incessant, within thyself, equal to any, <lb/>divine as any;</l>
                     <l>Thee in an education grown of thee&#8212;in teachers, <lb/>studies, students, born of thee;</l>
                     <l>Thee in thy democratic f&#234;tes, en masse&#8212;thy high <lb/>original festivals, operas, lecturers, preachers;</l>
                     <l>Thee in thy ultimata, (the preparations only now <lb/>completed&#8212;the edifice on sure foundations <lb/>tied,)</l>
                     <l>Thee in thy pinnacles, intellect, thought, thy <choice><sic>top&#8211; <lb/>most</sic><corr>top&#8211;most</corr></choice> rational joys&#8212;thy love, and godlike 
                     <choice><sic>aspira&#8211; <lb/>tion</sic><corr>aspiration</corr></choice>,</l>
                     <l>In thy resplendent coming literati&#8212;thy <choice><sic>full&#8211;lung'd</sic><corr>full&#8211;lunged</corr></choice> <lb/>orators&#8212;thy sacerdotal bards&#8212;kosmic savans,</l>
                     <l>These! these in thee, (certain to come,) to&#8211;day  I <choice><sic>pro&#8211; <lb/>phecy</sic><corr>prophecy</corr></choice>.</l>
                  </lg>
               </lg>
               
               <lg type="section"><head type="sub">5.</head>
                  <lg type="linegroup">
                     <l>Land tolerating all&#8212;accepting all&#8212;not for the good <lb/>alone&#8212;all good for thee;</l>
                     <l>Land in the realms of God to be a realm unto <choice><sic>thy&#8211; <lb/>self</sic><corr>thyself</corr></choice>;</l>
                     <l>Under the rule of God to be a rule unto thyself.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg type="linegroup">
                     <l>(Lo! where arise three peerless stars,</l>
                     <l>To by thy natal stars, my country&#8212;Ensemble&#8212;<choice><sic>Evo&#8211; <lb/>lution</sic><corr>Evolution</corr></choice>&#8212;Freedom,</l>
                     <l>Set in the sky of Law.)</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg type="linegroup">
                     <l>Land of unprecedented faith&#8212;God's faith!</l>
                     <l>Thy soil, thy very subsoil, all <choice><sic>upheav'd</sic><corr>upheaved</corr></choice>;</l>
                     <l>The general inner earth, so long, so sedulously draped <lb/>over, now and hence for what it is boldly laid <lb/>bare,</l>
                     <l><choice><sic>Open'd</sic><corr>Opened</corr></choice> by thee to heaven's light, for benefit or bale.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg type="linegroup">
                     <l>Not for success alone;</l>
                     <l>Not to fair&#8211;sail unintermitted always;</l>
                     <l>The storm shall dash thy face&#8212;the murk of war, and <lb/>worse than war, shall cover thee all over;</l>
                     <l>(Wert capable of war&#8212;its tug and trials? Be <choice><sic>capa&#8211; <lb/>ble</sic><corr>capable</corr></choice> of peace; its trials;</l>
                     <l>For the tug and mortal strain of nations come at last <lb/>in peace&#8212;not war;)</l>
                     <l>In many a smiling mask death shall approach, <choice><sic>be&#8211; <lb/>guiling</sic><corr>beguiling</corr></choice> thee&#8212;thou in disease shalt swelter;</l>
                     <l>The livid cancer spread its hideous claws, clinging <lb/>upon thy breasts, seeing to strike thee deep <lb/>within;</l>
                     <l>Consumption of the worst&#8212;moral consumption&#8212; <lb/>shall rouge thy face with hectic:</l>
                     <l>But thou shalt face thy fortunes, thy diseases, and <lb/>surmount them all,</l>
                     <l>Whatever they are to&#8211;day, and whatever through time <lb/>they may be,</l>
                     <l>They each and all shall lift, and pass away, and cease <lb/>from thee;</l>
                     <l>While thou, Time's spirals rounding&#8212;out of thyself, <lb/>thyself still extricating, fusing,</l>
                     <l>Equable, natural, mystical Union thou&#8212;(the mortal <lb/>with immortal blent,)</l>
                     <l>Shalt soar toward the fulfilment of the future&#8212;the <lb/>spirit of the body and the mind,</l>
                     <l>The Soul&#8212;its destinies.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg type="linegroup">
                     <l>the Soul, its destinies&#8212;the real real,</l>
                     <l>(Purport of all these apparitions of the real;)</l>
                     <l>In thee, America, the Soul, its destinies;</l>
                     <l>Thou globe of globes! thou wonder nebulous!</l>
                     <l>By many a throe of heat and cold <choice><sic>convuls'd</sic><corr>convulsed</corr></choice>&#8212;(by <lb/>these thyself solidifying;)</l>
                     <l>Thou mental, moral orb! thou New, indeed new, <lb/>Spiritual World!</l>
                     <l>The Present holds thee not&#8212;for such vast growth as <lb/>thine&#8212;for such <choice><sic>unparallel'd</sic><corr>unparalleled</corr></choice> flight as thine,</l>
                     <l>The Future only holds thee, and can hold thee.</l>
                  </lg>
               </lg>
            </lg>
               
            <lg type="poem">
              <head type="main-authorial"><hi rend="italic">THE MYSTIC TRUMPETER.</hi></head>
               <lg type="section"><head type="sub">1.</head>
                  <lg type="linegroup">
                     <l>H<hi rend="smallcaps">ark</hi>! some wild trumpeter&#8212;some strange musician,</l>
                     <l>Hovering uneen in air, vibrates capricious tunes <choice><sic>to&#8211; <lb/>night</sic><corr>tonight</corr></choice>.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg type="linegroup">
                     <l>I hear thee, trumpeter&#8212;listening, alert, I catch thy <lb/>notes,</l>
                     <l>Now pouring, whirling like a tempest round me,</l>
                     <l>Now low, subdued&#8212;now in the distance lost.</l>
                  </lg>
               </lg>
               
               <lg type="section"><head type="sub">2.</head>
                  <lg type="linegroup">
                     <l>Come nearer, bodiless one&#8212;haply, in thee resounds</l>
                     <l>Some dead composer&#8212;haply thy pensive life</l>
                     <l>Was <choice><sic>fill'd</sic><corr>filled</corr></choice> with aspirations high&#8212;<choice><sic>unform'd</sic><corr>unformed</corr></choice> ideals,</l>
                     <l>Waves, oceans musical, chaotically surging,</l>
                     <l>That now, ecstatic ghost, close to me bending, thy <lb/>cornet echoing, pealing,</l>
                     <l>Gives not to no one's ears but mine&#8212;but freely gives <lb/>to mine,</l>
                     <l>That I may thee translate.</l>
                  </lg>
               </lg>
                  
               <lg type="section"><head type="sub">3.</head>
                  <lg type="linegroup">
                     <l>Blow, trumpeter, free and clear&#8212;I follow thee,</l>
                     <l>While at thy liquid prelude, glad, serene,</l>
                     <l>The fretting world, the streets, the noisy hours of <lb/>day, withdraw;</l>
                     <l>A holy calm descends, like dew, upon me,</l>
                     <l>I walk, in cool refreshing night, the walks of <choice><sic>Para&#8211; <lb/>dise</sic><corr>Paradise</corr></choice>,</l>
                     <l>I scent the grass, the moist air, and the roses;</l>
                     <l>Thy song expands my <choice><sic>numb'd</sic><corr>numbed</corr></choice>, imbonded spirit&#8212;thou <lb/>freest, launchest me,</l>
                     <l>Floating and basking upon Heaven's lake.</l>
                  </lg>
               </lg>
                  
               <lg type="section"><head type="sub">4.</head>
                  <lg type="linegroup">
                     <l>Blow again, trumpeter! and for my sensuous eyes,</l>
                     <l>Bring the old pageants&#8212;show the feudal world.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg type="linegroup">
                     <l>What charm thy music works!&#8212;thou makest pass <choice><sic>be&#8211; <lb/>fore</sic><corr>before</corr></choice> me,</l>
                     <l>Ladies and cavaliers long dead&#8212;barons are in their <lb/>castle halls&#8212;the troubadours are singing;</l>
                     <l><choice><sic>Arm'd</sic><corr>Armed</corr></choice> knights go forth to redress wrongs&#8212;some in <lb/>quest of the Holy Graal:</l>
                     <l>I see the tournament&#8212;I see the contestants, encased <lb/>in heavy armor, seated on stately, champing <lb/>horses;</l>
                     <l>I hear the shouts&#8212;the sounds of blows and smiting <lb/>steel:</l>
                     <l>I see the Crusaders' tumultuous armies&#8212;Hark! how <lb/>the cymbals clang!</l>
                     <l>Lo! where the monks walk in advance, bearing the <lb/>cross on high!</l>
                 </lg>
               </lg>
               
               <lg type="section"><head type="sub">5.</head>
                  <lg type="linegroup">
                     <l>Blow again, trumpeter! and for thy theme,</l>
                     <l>Take now the enclosing theme of all&#8212;the solvent and <lb/>the setting;</l>
                     <l><hi rend="italic">Love</hi>, that is the pulse of all&#8212;the sustenance and the <lb/>pang;</l>
                     <l>The heart of many and woman all for love;</l>
                     <l>No other theme but love&#8212;knitting, enclosing, <choice><sic>all&#8211;dif&#8211; <lb/>fusing</sic><corr>all&#8211;diffusing</corr></choice> love.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg type="linegroup">
                     <l>O, see how the immortal phantoms crowd around me!</l>
                     <l>I see the vast alembic ever working&#8212;I see and know <lb/>the flames that heat the world;</l>
                     <l>The glow, the blush, the beating hearts of lovers,</l>
                     <l>So blissful happy some&#8212;and some so silent, dark, and <lb/>nigh to death:</l>
                     <l>Love, that is all the earth to lovers&#8212;Love, that mocks <lb/>time and space;</l>
                     <l>Love, that is day and night&#8212;Love, that is sun and moon and stars;</l>
                     <l>Love, that is crimson, sumptuous, sick with perfume;</l>
                     <l>No other words, but words of love&#8212;no other thought <lb/>but Love.</l>
                  </lg>
               </lg>
               
               <lg type="section"><head type="sub">6.</head>
                  <lg type="linegroup">
                     <l>Blow again, trumpeter&#8212;conjure war's wild alarums.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg type="linegroup">
                     <l>Swift to thy spell, a shuddering hum like distant <lb/>thunder rolls;</l>
                     <l>Lo! where the <choice><sic>arm'd</sic><corr>armed</corr></choice> men hasten&#8212;Lo! mid the <lb/>clouds of dust, the glint of bayonets;</l>
                     <l>I see the grime&#8211;faced cannoniers&#8212;I mark the rosy <lb/>flash amid the smoke&#8212;I hear the cracking of the <lb/>guns:</l>
                     <l>&#8212;Nor war alone&#8212;thy fearful music&#8211;song, wild player, <lb/>brings every sight of fear,</l>
                     <l>The deeds of ruthless brigands&#8212;rapine, murder&#8212;I <lb/>hear the cries for help!</l>
                     <l>I see the ships foundering at sea&#8212;I behold on deck, and <lb/>below deck, the terrible tableaux.</l>
                  </lg>
               </lg>
               
               <lg type="section"><head type="sub">7.</head>
                  <lg type="linegroup">
                     <l>O trumpeter! methinks I am myself the instrument <lb/>thou playest!</l>
                     <l>Thou <choice><sic>melt'st</sic><corr>meltest</corr></choice> my heart, my brain&#8212;thou movest, drawest, changest them, at will:</l>
                     <l>And now thy sullen notes send darkness through me;</l>
                     <l>Thou takest away all cheering light&#8212;all hope:</l>
                     <l>I see the enslaved, the overthrown, the hurt, the <choice><sic>op&#8211; <lb/>prest</sic><corr>opprest</corr></choice> of the whole earth;</l>
                     <l>I feel the measureless shame and humiliation of my <lb/>race&#8212;it becomes all mine;</l>
                     <l>Mine too the revenges of humanity&#8212;the wrongs of <lb/>ages&#8212;baffled feuds and hatreds;</l>
                     <l>Utter defeat upon me weighs&#8212;all lost! the foe <choice><sic>vic&#8211; <lb/>torious</sic><corr>victorious</corr></choice>!</l>
                     <l>(Yet <choice><sic>'mid</sic><corr>amid</corr></choice> the ruins Pride colossal stands, unshaken to <lb/>the last;</l>
                     <l>Endurance, resolution, to the last.)</l>
                  </lg>
               </lg>
               
               <lg type="section"><head type="sub">8.</head>
                  <lg type="linegroup">
                     <l>Now, trumpeter, for thy close,</l>
                     <l>Vouchsafe a higher strain than any yet;</l>
                     <l>Sing to my soul&#8212;renew its languishing faith and <lb/>hope;</l>
                     <l>Rouse up my slow belief&#8212;give me some vision of the <lb/>future;</l>
                     <l>Give me, for once, its prophecy and joy.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg type="linegroup">
                     <l>O glad, exulting, culminating song!</l>
                     <l>A vigor more than earth's is in thy notes!</l>
                     <l>Marches of victory&#8212;man <choice><sic>disenthrall'd</sic><corr>disenthralled</corr></choice>the <choice><sic>con&#8211; <lb/>queror</sic><corr>conqueror</corr></choice> at last!</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg type="linegroup">
                     <l>Hymns to the universal God, from universal Man&#8212; <lb/>all joy!</l>
                     <l>A reborn race appears&#8212;a perfect World, all joy!</l>
                     <l>Women and Men, in wisdom, innocence and health&#8212;all joy!</l>
                     <l>Riotous, laughing, bacchanals, <choice><sic>fill'd</sic><corr>filled</corr></choice> with joy!</l>
                     <l>War, sorrow, suffering gone&#8212;The rank earth purged <lb/>&#8212;nothing but joy left!</l>
                     <l>The ocean <choice><sic>fill'd</sic><corr>filled</corr></choice> with joy&#8212;the atmosphere all joy!</l>
                     <l>Joy! Joy! in freedom, worship, love! Joy in the <lb/>ecstacy of life!</l>
                     <l>Enough to merely be! Enough to breathe!</l>
                     <l>Joy! Joy! all over Joy!</l>
                  </lg>
               </lg>
            </lg>
            
            <lg type="poem">
               <head type="main-authorial"><hi rend="italic">O STAR OF FRANCE!</hi></head>
               <head type="sub">1870&#8211;71</head>
               <lg type="section"><head type="sub">1.</head>
                  <lg type="linegroup">
                     <l>O S<hi rend="smallcaps">tar</hi> of France!</l>
                     <l>The brightness of thy hope and strength and fame,</l>
                     <l>Like some proud ship that led the fleet so long,</l>
                     <l>Beseems to&#8212;day a wreck, driven by the gale&#8212;a <choice><sic>mast&#8211; <lb/>less</sic><corr>mast&#8211;less</corr></choice> hulk;</l>
                     <l>And <choice><sic>'mid</sic><corr>amid</corr></choice> its teeming, <choice><sic>madden'd</sic><corr>maddened</corr></choice>, <choice><sic>half&#8211;drown'd</sic>
                     <corr>half&#8212;drowned</corr></choice> <lb/>crowds,</l>
                     <l>Nor helm nor helmsman.</l>
                  </lg>
               </lg>
                  
               <lg type="section"><head type="sub">2.</head>
                  <lg type="linegroup">
                     <l>Dim, smitten star!</l>
                     <l>Orb not of France alone&#8212;pale symbol of my soul, its <lb/>dearest hopes,</l>
                     <l>The struggle and the daring&#8212;rage divine for the liberty,</l>
                     <l>Of aspirations toward the far ideal&#8212;enthusiast's <lb/>dreams of brotherhood,</l>
                     <l>Of terror to the tyrant and the priest.</l>
                  </lg>
               </lg>
                  
               <lg type="section"><head type="sub">3.</head>
                  <lg type="linegroup">
                     <l>Star crucified! by traitors sold!</l>
                     <l>Star panting <choice><sic>o'er</sic><corr>over</corr></choice> a land of death&#8212;heroic land!</l>
                     <l>Strange, passionate, mocking, frivolous land.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg type="linegroup">
                     <l>Miserable! yet for thy errors, vanities, sins, I will not <lb/>now rebuke thee;</l>
                     <l>Thy unexampled woes and pangs have <choice><sic>quell'd</sic><corr>quelled</corr></choice> them <lb/>all,</l>
                     <l>And left thee sacred.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg type="linegroup">
                     <l>In that amid thy man faults, thou ever aimedst <lb/>highly,</l>
                     <l>In that thou surely wakedst weeping from thy <lb/><choice><sic>drugg'd</sic><corr>drugged</corr></choice> sleep,</l>
                     <l>In that alone, among thy sisters, thou, Giantess, didst <lb/>rend the ones that shamed thee,</l>
                     <l>In that thou couldst not, wouldst not, wear the usual <lb/>chains,</l>
                     <l>This cross, thy livid face, thy pierced hands and feet,</l>
                     <l>The spear thrust in thy side.</l>
                  </lg>
               </lg>
                
               <lg type="section"><head type="sub">4.</head>
                  <lg type="linegroup">
                     <l>O star! O ship of France, beat back and baffled long!</l>
                     <l>Bear up, O smitten orb! O ship, continue on!</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg type="linegroup">
                     <l>Sure, as the ship of all, the Earth itself,</l>
                     <l>Product of deathly fire and turbulent chaos,</l>
                     <l>Forth from its spasms of fury and its poisons,</l>
                     <l>Issuing at last in perfect power and beauty,</l>
                     <l>Onward, beneath the sun, following its course,</l>
                     <l>So thee, O ship of France!</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg type="linegroup">
                     <l><choice><sic>Finish'd</sic><corr>Finished</corr></choice> the days, the clouds <choice><sic>dispell'd</sic><corr>dispelled</corr></choice>,</l>
                     <l>The travail <choice><sic>o'er</sic><corr>o'er</corr></choice>, the European world,</l>
                     <l>(In gladness, answering thence, as face afar to face, <lb/>reflecting ours, Columbia,)</l>
                     <l>Again thy star, O France&#8212;fair, lustrous star,</l>
                     <l>In heavenly peace, clearer, more bright than ever,</l>
                     <l>Shall beam mortal.</l>
                  </lg>
               </lg>
             </lg>
               
             <lg type="poem">
               <head type="main-authorial"><hi rend="italic">BY BROAD POTOMAC'S SHORE.</hi></head>
                <lg type="section"><head type="sub">1.</head>
                  <lg type="linegroup">
                     <l>B<hi rend="smallcaps">y</hi> broad Potomac's shore&#8212;again, old tongue!</l>
                     <l>(Still uttering&#8212;still ejaculating&#8212;canst never cease <lb/>this babble?)</l>
                     <l>Again, old heart so gay&#8212;again to you, your sense, <lb/>the full flush spring returning;</l>
                     <l>Again the freshness and the odors&#8212;again Virginia's <lb/>summer sky, pellucid blue and silver,</l>
                     <l>Again the forenoon purple of the hills,</l>
                     <l>Again the deathless grass, so noiseless, soft and green,</l>
                     <l>Again the blood&#8211;red roses blooming.</l>
                  </lg>
               </lg>
                  
               <lg type="section"><head type="sub">2.</head>
                  <lg type="linegroup">
                     <l>Perfume this book of mine, O blood&#8211;red roses!</l>
                     <l>Lave subtly with your waters every line, Potomac!</l>
                     <l>Give me of you, O spring, before I close, to put <lb/>between its pages!</l>
                     <l>O forenoon purple of the hills, before I close, of you!</l>
                     <l>O deathless grass, of you!</l>
                  </lg>
               </lg>
            </lg>   
         </div1>
            
         <div1 type="ad">
            <head type="sub"><hi rend="italic">A<hi rend="smallcaps">dvertisement</hi></hi>.</head>
            <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-full"/>
            <div2 type="section">
               <head type="main-authorial">WALT WHITMAN'S BOOKS.</head>
               <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-full"/>
               <head type="sub">Can be Ordered of any Bookseller.</head>
               <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-full"/>
               <p><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi></hi>. Complete. Edition 1872. Comprises all 
               the Poems of the Editions of 1855, '57, '60, and '67; with added 
               Pieces. 504 pages, cloth. Price, &#36;3.</p>
               <p>A reader taking up this volume for the first time needs an 
               emphatic warning given him in advance. Of "poetry" in the 
               accepted sense, and according to the current market supply of that 
               article in Europe and America, he must be notified to expect little 
               or nothing&#8212;no rhyme, nor regularity, nor love stories, nor any of 
               the sugar&#8211;flavors or ornamentations customary in verse. He will 
               be perplexed still worse. Ordinary rules of correcting writing, so as 
               to be understood while you go along, are not followed b this voice 
               from the sea&#8211;beach&#8211;this chanter from Paumanok.<ref target="#fn3">*</ref> Neither will 
               the book bear any analogy. Most poets are profitably compared 
               with, and set off by, their brother bards, like flowers in a bouquet; 
               but it would only be an aggravation to compare Walt Whitman 
               with others&#8212;either with the great past poets, r the later ones of 
               England, sch as Tennyson or Browning; or those of our own 
               country, Bryant, Emerson, or Longfellow. L<hi rend="smallcaps">eaves of</hi> G<hi rend="smallcaps">rass</hi> is 
               <hi rend="italic">sui generis</hi>, and if not advanced beyond all, of incomparable excellence 
               and altitude, the work is (as stoutly maintained by many 
               cultivated people) a failure and fraud, sinking below every thing. 
               There is no middle ground.</p>
               <p>The Paumanok poet also differs from others in an avowed purpose 
               to express his own special personality out and out. According 
               to the theory of his verse, a legitimate and even indispensable part 
               of it is to "celebrate" and clearly define the individual identity 
               he himself either is, or of which he contains the elements, and aims 
               to become. That he only <hi rend="italic">writes about himself</hi>&#8212;a criticism often 
               sneeringly brought against him&#8212;is, in fact, the very object of his 
               appearance in literature, which is, briefly, to formulate in a poem, 
               with unprecedented candor, a complete human being, body, mind, 
               emotions, soul. It is himself typically, however, and for an ultimate 
               purpose.</p>
               
               <note xml:id="fn3" type="footnote" place="bottom">
                  * Paumanok, (or Paumanake, or Paumanack,) the aboriginal name of Long 
                  Island, New&#8211;York. A peculiar region, over a hundred miles long, shaped like 
                  a fish&#8212;plenty of sea&#8211;shore, sandy, stormy, uninviting the horizon boundless, 
                  the air healthy, but too strong for invalids, the bays a wonderful resort for 
                  aquatic birds, the south&#8211;side meadows covered with salt hay, the soil of the 
                  island generally tough, but good for the locust&#8211;tree, the apple orchard, and 
                  the blackberry, and with numberless springs of the sweetest water in the 
                  world.
                  Years ago, among the bay&#8211;man&#8212;a strong, wild race, now extinct, or rather 
                  entirely changed&#8212;a native of Long Island was called a <hi rend="italic">Paumanacker</hi>, or 
                  <hi rend="italic">Creole&#8211;Paumanacker</hi>.
               </note>
               
               <p>The book weaves and twines in everywhere the different products, 
               climates, and all and each of the several United States, by 
               their nomenclature, the South as much as the North&#8212;not a single 
               State or city, and hardly a river or mountain left out; all knitted and 
               twisted together, so that their entire geography and hydrography 
               are fused in its pages. Amid these, the figure of the author continually 
               appears, recording his own personal habits, memoranda, 
               portraits,<ref target="#fn4">*</ref> surrounded by his times, his country, the Secession war, 
               the great inventions and leading occurrences, the rendition of 
               Burns in Boston, the visits of the Prince of Wales, the Japanese 
               embassy, the arrival of the Great Eastern, the meteors of 1859, the 
               death of President Lincoln, the Peabody bequests, the return of 
               the armies, their review in Washington in 1865, and similar accompaniments.</p>
               <p>But inside of all, and the real summing &#8211;up of all, and running 
               through the book, and holding it together, the verterber&#8211;purpose 
               of L<hi rend="smallcaps">eaves of</hi> G<hi rend="italic">rass</hi> is to present the model and ideal portrait
               &#8212;for the service of the new World, and designed to be gradually 
               absorbed in it&#8212;of a complete, healthy, heroic, industrial, A<hi rend="italic">verage</hi>
               M<hi rend="italic">odern</hi> M<hi rend="italic">an</hi>, physical, emotional, moral, mental, patriotic, spiritual&#8212;
               a grander, better, completer son, brother, husband, father, 
               citizen, friend, than any yet&#8212;formed and shaped in consonance 
               with latest, largest science, with the genius of American democracy, 
               and with the requirements of daily business in work&#8211;shop or office, 
               or on farm, or ship&#8211;board;&#8212;a model also of <hi rend="smallcaps">the</hi> A<hi rend="smallcaps">verage</hi>
               W<hi rend="smallcaps">oman</hi>, equally modern and heroic&#8212;a daughter, wife, mother, citizen, 
               also better, completer than any yet. The poems throughout 
               tend to construct such definite, living Personalities, male and 
               female, immensely animal, with immense passions, immense amativeness, 
               immense paternity in the man, immense maternity in the 
               woman&#8212;and then immenser far in moral conscience and decorum, 
               and in constantly realizing the control, direct and indirect, of the 
               divine laws, through all and over all forever. That "Unprecedented 
               health and hilarity, and a constitutional aversion to meanness 
               and impurity, would be the characteristics of a race, born and 
               grown in consonance with these poems," is said to be the haughty 
               claim made by the author himself. </p>
               <p>The history of the gradual development of Walt Whitman's 
               poems is significant, almost geologic. The author having formed 
               his plan, commenced carrying it out at the age of 35 ears&#8212;"in 
               perfect health, hoping to cease not till death." This was in Brooklyn, 
               new &#8211;York, in 1855. The small nucleus&#8211;volume then issued 
               was received, both in England and America&#8212;as far as it attracted 
               any attention&#8212;with unmitigated torrents of mockery and derisive 
               laughter&#8212;the echoes of which are still occasionally heard. [See
               
                  <note xml:id="fn4" type="footnote" place="bottom">
                     * His portrait, as in 1872, (age 52) photographed from life, in Washington, 
                     precedes the text; and in "Crossing Brooklyn Ferry," (composed at the time,) 
                     is given another picture, in shirt&#8211;sleeves and open neck, impromptu, daguereotyped 
                     from life by Gabriel Harrison, Fulton street, Brooklyn, on a warm 
                     July day in 1854.
                     [The portraits are deferred till next edition.]
                  </note>
                  
               John Burrough's little published volume of "N<hi rend="smallcaps">otes</hi>."] Upon 
               and around this nucleus&#8211;volume of 1855, have since been steadily 
               formed gradual accretions, published in 1857, in 1860, in 1867, and 
               lastly in 1872&#8212;each part of these accretions designed strictly with 
               reference to its relative fitness in the whole&#8212;"the completed 
               volume being best understood," as has been said, "when viewed 
               as such a series of growths, or strata, rising out from a settled 
               foundation or centre."</p>
               <p>"There is probably no analogous case in the history of literature where the 
               result of a profound artistic plan or conception&#8212;first launched forth, and briefly, 
               yet sufficiently exemplified, as in the small volume of the L<hi rend="smallcaps">eaves</hi> of 1855, taking 
               for foundation Man in his fulness of blood, power, amativevness, health, physique, 
               and as standing in the midst of the objective world&#8212;a plan so steadily 
               adhered to, yet so audaciously and freely built out of and upon, and with such 
               epic consistency, after that start of 1855, developed in '57, '60' and '66, in successive 
               moral, esthetic, and religious stages, each absorbing the previous ones, 
               but striding on far ahead of them&#8212;gradually made more and more emotional, 
               meditative, and patriotic&#8211;vitalized, heated to almost unbearable fervency by 
               the author's personal part in the war, composing his songs of it in actual contact 
               with its subjects, on the very field, or surrounded by the wounded "after 
               the battle brought in"&#8212;chanting undismayed the strong chant of the Inseparable 
               Union, amid the vehement crises and stormy dangers of the period; and so 
               gradually arriving at the completed book of 1871&#8211;2, and crowning all in it with 
               the electric and solemn poems of death and immortality&#8212;has so justified, and 
               beyond measure justified, its first ambitious plan and promise."&#8212;<hi rend="italic">John Burrough's</hi> 
               N<hi rend="smallcaps">otes</hi>.</p>
               <p>The basis on which the work stands will probably finally be 
               discovered and agreed to be the Religious basis&#8212;the reference of 
               every possible event to a divine purpose, and unfolding. The 
               book is the song of Idealism. Underneath every page lurks the 
               conviction that all we fancy we see, may be but apparitions&#8212; 
               and that</p>
               <p>"The real Something has yet to be known."</p>
               <p>Its scope and purpose are, therefore, by no means merely intellectual, 
               or ecclesiastical, or esthetic. Using the term in its latest 
               and largest, and not all in its dogmatic and scholastic sense, 
               Walt Whitman's poetry is, in its intention, <hi rend="italic">philosophic</hi>. It is beyond 
               the moral law, and will probably therefore always appal 
               many. The moral law, it is true, is present, penetrating the verse, 
               like shafts of light. But the whole relentless kosmos out of which 
               come monsters and crime and the inexhaustible germs of all the 
               heat of sex, and all the lawless rut and arrogant greed of the universe, 
               and especially of the human race, are also there. Strange 
               and paradoxical are these pages. They accept and celebrate nature 
               in absolute faith. Then, as over and out of some unbounded 
               sea of turmoil, and whirl and hiss of stormy waves, hurrying and 
               tumbling and chaotic&#8212;which they largely are&#8212;still, b attempts, 
               indications, at least, rise voices, sounds of the mightiest strength 
               and gladdest hope yet given to man, with undismayed, unfaltering 
               faith in destiny and life.</p>
               <p>"The history of the book, thus considered, not only resembles and tallies, 
               in certain respects, the development of the great System of Idealistic Philosophy 
               in Germany, by the 'illustrious four'&#8212;except that the development of 
               L<hi rend="smallcaps">eaves of</hi> G<hi rend="smallcaps">rass</hi> has been carried on within the region of a single mind,&#8212;but 
               it is to be demonstrated, by study and comparison, that the same theory of he 
               essential identity of the spiritual and the material worlds, the shows of nature, 
               the progress of civilization, the play of passions, the human intellect, and the 
               relations between it and the concrete universe, which Kant prepared the way 
               for, and Fichte, Schelling, and Hegel have given expression and statement in 
               their system of transcendental Metaphysics&#8212;this authors has, with equal entirety, 
               expressed and stated in L<hi rend="smallcaps">eaves of</hi> G<hi rend="smallcaps">rass</hi>, from a poet's point of view 
               &#8212;singing afresh, out of it, the song of the visible and invisible worlds&#8212;renewing, 
               reconstructing, consistently with the modern genius, and deeper and wider 
               than ever, the promises of immortality&#8212;endowing the elements of faith and 
               pride with a vigor and <hi rend="italic">ensemble</hi> before unknown&#8212;and furnishing to the measureless 
               audience of humanity the only great Imaginative Work it yet possesses, 
               in which the objective universe and Man, his soul, are observed and 
               outlined, and the theory of Human Personality and Character projected, from 
               the anterior and hidden, but absolute background, of that magnificent System."
               &#8212;<hi rend="italic">John Burroughs's</hi> N<hi rend="smallcaps">otes</hi>.</p>
               <p>it will always remain, however, impossible to clearly and fully 
               state either the theory of Walt Whitman's composition, or describe 
               his poems, its results. They may be absorbed out of themselves, 
               but only after many perusals. They are elusive and puzzling, 
               like their model, Nature, and form, in face, a <hi rend="italic">person</hi>, perhaps 
               a <hi rend="italic">spirit</hi>, more than a book. They read clearest t&#234;te&#8211;&#224;&#8211;t&#234;te, 
               and in the open air, or by the sea, or on the mountains, or in one's 
               own room, alone, at night. They are to be inhaled, like perfumes, 
               and felt, like the magnetism of a presence. They require affinity 
               in the tastes and qualities of the reader. There is, mainly, that in 
               them akin to concrete objects, the earth, the animals, storms, the 
               actual sunrise or sunset, and not to the usual fine writing or imagery 
               of poems. Yet their subject is not abstract or irrational Nature, 
               but living, heart&#8211;beating humanity, with al its interests and 
               aspirations, its sadness and its joy.</p>
               <p>It is to be added that the whole work, as it now stands, the 
               complete result of the several accretions, singularly hinges on the 
               late Secession war.</p>
               
               <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-full"/>
               <p><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Democratic Vistas</hi></hi>. Prose. 64 pages. Price, 75 cts.</p>
               <p>"In D<hi rend="smallcaps">emocratic</hi> V<hi rend="smallcaps">istas</hi> I seek to make realized the appalling 
               vacuum, our times and here, of any great Imaginative Literature 
               or Art, or spirit of Literature or Art, fit to nourish a Republican 
               and Religious people; and to suggest and prophecy such a Literature 
               and Art as the only means of sustaining and perpetuating 
               such a people. I wish to put on record the rough sketch or outline, 
               if no more, of a new breed of authors, poets, artists for America&#8212;
               comprehensive, Hegelian, Democratic, sacerdotal."&#8212;<hi rend="italic">Letter 
               from Walt Whitman</hi>.</p>
               
               <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-full"/>
               <p><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">After All, not to Create Only</hi></hi>. Poem. 24 pp. Price, 30 
               cts. Roberts Brothers, Boston.</p>
               <p>Delivered orally by the author, on invitation of the Managers of 
               the American Institute, in the midst of crowd examples of products, 
               goods, machinery, etc., gathered in a two&#8211;acre edifice, "the 
               Rink," on Third Avenue, New&#8211;York, at mid&#8211;day, September 7th, 
               1871. The piece celebrates Industrial life and Inventions, and 
               hinges on the grand design of the Institute to build a vast structure, 
               or group of structures, for a permanent and hitherto unequalled 
               Universal Rendezvous and Fair of specimens of all the 
               Trades, Materials, Engines, and manufactures of the working 
               World&#8212;and for Science and Art.</p>
               
               <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-full"/>
               <p><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">As a Strong Bird on Pinions Free</hi></hi>. Poems. 40 pp. 
               Price, 50 cts.</p>
               <p>The leading piece in this volume, and giving name to it, is the 
               Annual Commencement Poem, delivered on invitation of the Public 
               Literary Societies of Dartmouth College, N.H., June 26th, 1872. 
               It is an expression and celebration of the coming mentality and 
               literature of the United States&#8212;not only the great scientists 
               "already visible," but the great artists, poets, litt&#233;rateurs, yet 
               unknown.</p>
               <p>The "Mystic Trumpeter," and "Star of France," and indeed all 
               Walt Whitman's other pieces since 1871&#8211;'2, follow.</p>
               <p>These&#8212;the poems of the author's elder age&#8212;are the surplusage 
               of L<hi rend="smallcaps">eaves of</hi> G<hi rend="smallcaps">rass</hi>&#8212;the wake following that volume, as the eddies 
               behind a ship.</p>
               
               <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-full"/>
               <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-full"/>
               <p><hi rend="italic">Book by</hi> J<hi rend="smallcaps">ohn</hi> B<hi rend="italic">urroughs</hi> <hi rend="italic">on Walt Whitman</hi>.</p>
               <p><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Notes on Walt Whitman as Poet and Person</hi></hi>. By 
               J<hi rend="smallcaps">ohn</hi> B<hi rend="italic">urroughs</hi>. Second edition. Cloth. Pp. 126. Published 
               by J.S. Redfield, 140 Fulton street, New&#8211;York. Price, $1.</p>
               <p>These "N<hi rend="italic">otes</hi>" have a double, or perhaps triple purpose&#8212;to 
               give what may be called the typographical history of L<hi rend="smallcaps">eaves of</hi> 
               G<hi rend="smallcaps">rass</hi>, especially of its first or initial edition, with the reception 
               thereof in 1855; and also of the issues of 1857, '60, '67, and '72; to 
               present various literary and critical opinions upon the volume and 
               on poetry generally, and on "Beauty," with reference to Walt 
               Whitman's method; and also to furnish some candid personal 
               memoranda and a short biographical sketch of the Paumanok 
               bard. By the latter it appears he was born in 1819, brought up 
               in Brooklyn and new&#8211;York, and received only an ordinary education. 
               Mr. Burroughs, defending these personal memoranda, says: 
               "I doubt whether Walt Whitman's writings can be realized or 
               understood, except through first knowing or getting a true notion 
               of the corporeal mean and his manners, and coming in rapport with 
               them." The "Notes" are most interesting in these characteristic 
               personal facts, gathered by a shrewd and perceptive writer, a born 
               naturalist, who has had an intimate acquaintance with his subject, 
               indoors and outdoors, for many years, and who speaks from a 
               friendly point of view.</p>
               <p>Walt Whitman personally is a study, affording the strongest 
               lights and shades. With all his hauteur and his instincts of perfection, 
               he by no means sets up for a saint, but is a  full&#8211;blood 
               fellow, with a life showing past blunders and missteps, and a 
               spirit not only tolerant toward weak and sinful mortals, but probably 
               a secret leaning toward them. Then he has not escaped the 
               fate of Personalities who rouse public attention, and canards, by 
               originality and independence. Perhaps, too, he has that affectation 
               sometimes seen&#8212;a grim amusement in tacitly taunting and 
               inviting them. Singularly simple and plain, few men are so beloved 
               as he&#8212;few have ever so magnetized; yet none afford more 
               temptation to caricature, or bogus anecdotes. The late summing&#8211;up 
               of a first&#8211;rate judge of human nature, that <hi rend="italic">personal knowledge</hi> 
               of him unerringly dissipates such fictions, is the best disposal of 
               this point.</p>
               <p>These&#8212;the poems of the author's elder age&#8212;are the surplusage 
                  of L<hi rend="smallcaps">eaves of</hi> G<hi rend="smallcaps">rass</hi>&#8212;the wake following that volume, as the eddies 
                  behind a ship.</p>
            </div2>
            
            <div2>
               <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-full"/>
            <head type="sub">All the forementioned Books for sale by</head>
               <p>J.S. REDFIELD, 140 Fulton street, New&#8211;York.</p>
               <p>B.F. FELT, 43 mercer street, New&#8211;York.</p>
               <p>SAMPSON LOW AND CO., 188 Fleet St., London.</p>
               <p>TRUBNER &#38; CO., 8 AND 60 Paternoster Row, London.</p>
            </div2>
            
            <div2>
               <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-full"/>
               <head type="main-authorial">FOREIGN CRITICISM ON WALT WHITMAN.</head>
               <p>A very lengthy, and in some respects remarkable criticism, on 
               the poems of Walt Whitman, with full biographical details of 
               that personage, have just appeared in a leading Scandinavian 
               monthly magazine, <hi rend="italic">For Ide og Virkelighed</hi>, ("For the idea and 
               Reality,") at Copenhagen, Denmark. Like the '<hi rend="italic">Westminster Review</hi>' 
               of last summer, the <hi rend="italic">Ide</hi> assumes that the poetical writers 
               of American have none of them hitherto accepted the current practical 
               facts, or spirit, or the democratic politics of the actual United 
               States, as the foundation or background of their poetry; but that 
               they have shunned or ignored those facts, and that their verse, to 
               all intents and purposes, has only been a continuation of the old 
               European poetic standards, feudal beliefs, and forms.</p>
               <p>The Scandinavian reviewer (like the <hi rend="italic">Westminster</hi> critic) asserts 
               that Whitman is the first literary <hi rend="italic">esthetik</hi> in America who has deliberately 
               based a lyrical utterance for the American States squarely 
               on their own present political, social, industrial, and even military 
               conditions and character, and who has undertaken to root 
               their verse on their own sol and give it hues and flavors of its 
               own; addressing himself not at all to the audiences of the 
               present and future of the American and democratic world.</p>
               <p>The <hi rend="italic">Ide</hi> (which makes great account of the <hi rend="italic">motif</hi> of the poems, 
               and brings prominently forward Mr. Whitman's small prose book, 
               "Democratic Vistas," from which it gives copious extracts) says it 
               must be candidly admitted that the American poet has not the elegance, 
               special melody, nor <hi rend="italic">recherch&#233;</hi> aroma of the accepted poets of 
               Europe or his own country; but that his compass and general harmony 
               are infinitely greater. He says the sweetness and spice, the 
               poetic <hi rend="italic">ennui</hi>, the tender longings, the exquisite art&#8211;finish of those 
               choice poets are mainly unseen and unmet in him&#8212;perhaps because 
               he cannot achieve them&#8212;more likely because he disdains 
               them. But there is an electric <hi rend="italic">living soul</hi> in his poetry, far more 
               fermenting and bracing. His wings do not glitter in their movement 
               from rich and vari&#8211;colored plumage, nor are his notes those 
               of the accustomed song&#8211;birds; but his flight is the flight of the 
               eagle.</p>
               <p>The current Danish version of the Old Testament is mentioned 
               b the Copenhagen reviewer as the nearest suggestion of the American 
               poet's style which he is able to give his readers. He translates, 
               "O Captain! my Captain!" and also prints it in the original. 
               He makes free use of Mr. John Burroughs's "Notes on Walt Whitman 
               as Poet and Person;" also, the "Woman's Estimate" of Mrs. 
               Anne Gilchrist, of England, and the previously mentioned <hi rend="italic">Westminster</hi> 
               criticism, by Professor Dowden, of Trinity College, Dublin.</p>
               <p>The <hi rend="italic">Ide</hi> concludes by saying of its own criticism&#8212;which occupies 
               fully half its February number&#8212;that it is beginning to be the 
               opinion of the most thoughtful men of the Old and New Worlds, 
               that the long prophesied and fondly expected new epoch of liberalization 
               for humanity, is more likely to prove, whenever it comes, 
               not so much a new epoch in politics and Government, but a new 
               epoch in literature; and that it has devoted its pages to an elaborate 
               statement of Walt Whitman, because of this epoch it considers 
               the advent of him and his writings the most significant sign.
               &#8212;<hi rend="italic">N.Y. Commercial Advertiser</hi>, April, 1872.</p>
               
               <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-full"/>
               <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-full"/>
               <p><hi rend="italic">Publications Critical and Personal Relating to L<hi rend="smallcaps">eaves of</hi> G<hi rend="smallcaps">rass</hi> 
               and their Author.</hi></p>
               <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-full"/>
               <p>L<hi rend="smallcaps">eaves of</hi> G<hi rend="smallcaps">rass</hi> I<hi rend="smallcaps">mprints</hi>. 64 pp. 16mo. Thayer &#38; Eldridge, 
               Boston, 1860.</p>
               <p>T<hi rend="smallcaps">he</hi> G<hi rend="smallcaps">ood</hi> G<hi rend="smallcaps">ray</hi> P<hi rend="smallcaps">oet</hi>: <hi rend="italic">a Vindication</hi>. By W.D. O'C<hi
               rend="smallcaps">onnor</hi>. Bunce &#38; Huntington, New&#8211;York, 1866. 46 pp. 8vo.</p>
               <p>R<hi rend="smallcaps">eview</hi>, "W<hi rend="smallcaps">alt</hi> W<hi rend="smallcaps">hitman</hi>, by F<hi rend="smallcaps">erdinand</hi> F<hi rend="smallcaps">reiligrath</hi> 
               with translations. Printed serially in three numbers <hi rend="italic">Augsburger Allgemeinen Zeitung</hi>, in 1868.</p>
               <p>A W<hi rend="smallcaps">oman's</hi> E<hi rend="smallcaps">stimate of</hi> W<hi rend="smallcaps">alt</hi> W<hi rend="smallcaps">hitman</hi>. Letters to W.M. 
               Rossetti from an Englishwoman, (Mrs. Ann. Gilchrist.) The 
               <hi rend="italic">Radical</hi> magazine for May, 1870, Boston, Mass.</p>
               <p>W<hi rend="smallcaps">estminster and</hi> F<hi rend="smallcaps">oreign</hi> Q<hi rend="smallcaps">uarterly</hi> R<hi rend="smallcaps">eview</hi>, England, 
               July, 1871. Article, "<hi rend="italic">The Poetry of Democracy: Walt Whitman</hi>>" 
               (By Prof. Edward Dowden, Trinity College, Dublin.)</p>
               <p>A S<hi rend="smallcaps">tudy of</hi> W<hi rend="smallcaps">alt</hi> W<hi rend="smallcaps">hitman, the</hi> P<hi rend="smallcaps">oet of</hi> M<hi rend="smallcaps">odern</hi> 
               D<hi rend="smallcaps">emocracy</hi>. by Hon. R<hi rend="smallcaps">cden</hi> N<hi rend="smallcaps">oel</hi>. The <hi rend="italic">Dark Blue</hi>, England, 
               October and November, 1871.</p>
               <p>F<hi rend="smallcaps">or</hi> I<hi rend="smallcaps">de og</hi> V<hi rend="smallcaps">irkelighed</hi>, (for the Idea and Reality,) monthly 
               magazine. Copenhagen, Denmark, February, 1872. Article, 
               "<hi rend="italic">Walt Whitman, det Amerikanske Demokratis Digter</hi>." By 
               Rudolf Schmidt.</p>
            </div2>
         </div1>   
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
